Curriculum Vitae

Peter Berrill

Born: 18th May, 1989 E-mail: peterberrill@aya.yale.edu

Nationality: Irish peter.berrill@tu-berlin.de

PERSONAL PROFILE

Peter is an industrial ecologist working on issues related to urban sustainability and is an active researcher in the fields of environmental assessment and climate change mitigation, with foci in the building, energy, and transport sectors. His current research project investigates the potential for integrated approaches for reducing energy demand and emissions from transport and buildings in European cities. His research has employed key industrial ecology methods of life cycle assessment, material stock and flow analysis, and environmental footprinting, in addition to traditional and novel statistical techniques. He is a keen musician and plays trumpet and violin.

EDUCATION

2016 - 2021	Doctor of Philosophy in Industrial Ecology – Yale University (USA).
	Thesis: "Energy and emissions in the U.S. residential sector, historical perspectives
	and opportunities for climate change mitigation". Supervisor Edgar G. Hertwich
2013 - 2015	Master of Science in Industrial Ecology – Double degree awarded by University of
	Graz (Austria) & TU Delft/Leiden University (Netherlands).
	Thesis Supervisor Edgar G. Hertwich
2014 - 2015	Master of Science – Waseda University (Japan), study exchange
2015	Master of Science – Norwegian University of Science and Technology Industrial
	Ecology Programme (Norway), research exchange
2009 - 2013	Bachelor of Engineering in Energy Systems Engineering, with minor in Civil
	Engineering – National University of Ireland, Galway (Ireland). Result: 1.1
	Thesis Supervisor Jamie Goggins
2008 - 2009	Higher Certificate in Music Performance – Royal Conservatoire of Scotland (UK)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2021-Present	Marie-Curie Individual Fellowship Post-doc researcher, Sustainability
	Economics of Human Settlements, TU Berlin. Guest Researcher MCC Berlin
2020	Doctoral intern researcher, Residential Buildings Research Group, National
	Renewable Energy Laboratory (USA)
2016-2021	Researcher and Doctoral Candidate, Yale University, Centre for Industrial
	Ecology.
2016	Business English Instructor, IBEC (Japan)
2015	Researcher, Industrial Ecology Programme, Norwegian University of Science and
	Technology (Norway)
2012	Intern civil, environmental engineer, Alan Kerins Project (Ireland, Zambia)
2009 – 2016	Musician and Music Tutor, EMK Productions and Freelance (Ireland)

ACADEMIC SERVICE

Board Member: International Society for Industrial Ecology, Life Cycle Sustainability Assessment Section (2023-)

Member of Scientific Committee for International Conference on Industrial Ecology, Leiden (2023)

Contributing Author: IPCC Assessment Report 6 Working Group 3, Buildings Chapter (2022)

Contributing Author: 'Ten insights from industrial ecology for the circular economy' (ISIE white paper, in press) Student Representative on Faculty Search Committee: Yale School of the Environment, Professor in Industrial

Ecology and Sustainable Systems (2020)

Leader of advisory group on reducing air travel GHG emissions from international conferences - International Society for Industrial Ecology

Peter Berrill – C.V. June 2023

Academic Referee: Performed peer-reviews of articles submitted to Journal of Industrial Ecology, Environmental

 $Science\ \&\ Technology, Environmental\ Research\ Letters, Joule,\ Scientific\ Data,\ Resources,$

Conservation & Recycling, Applied Energy, Nature Communications

GRANTS AND AWARDS

April 2021 Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions Individual Fellowship (2yr) for project "Sustainable Urban

Form For Integrated Climate Change Solutions" (SUFFICCS), €175,000

December 2018 Yale Institute for Biospheric Studies, Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grants, \$5,000 April 2017 Charles Kao Fund Research Grant, for project "Low-carbon Energy Development in 21st

Century Japan", \$5,000

March 2014 Sole student to win competitive award for one-semester study exchange to Waseda University

(Japan) as part of Erasmus Mundus MSc in Industrial Ecology

September 2013 Finalist in national competition for best final year project (bachelor thesis project) held by the

Republic of Ireland Regional Group of the Institution of Structural Engineers

March 2013 Erasmus Mundus Masters in Industrial Ecology (MIND) Category B scholarship award

(covering tuition, plus stipend totalling €16,000 over two years)

September 2012 National University of Ireland, Galway 'University Scholar', awarded to undergraduate

students achieving overall excellence, €500

RESEARCH MENTORING EXPERIENCE

Research mentor to early-stage doctoral student on project scoping and literature review related to high-resolution building materials stocks

2023 Research mentor to visiting master student for project on GIS and energy

data in French buildings

2022 Research mentor to master student for MSc dissertation "Enhancing the

sustainability of the residential sector with sufficiency measures"

2020 Research mentor to high-school student with Lumiere Education

2020 Research mentor to two masters students for summer internship research

projects: "US economy-wide non-hazardous waste generation: an extension the us Input-Output tables", and "Comparison of physical vs economic

allocation for airline GHG emissions"

2017 Research mentor to visiting masters student for thesis research project:

"Assessment of the Embodied and Operational Trade-offs of a U.S. Multi-Family Building With Changing Energy Codes and Different Climate

Zones"

OTHER SKILLS

First Language: English

Other Languages (European CEFR level): Japanese (Independent – B1), German (Basic user – A2)

Computer Programming Languages:

Programming languages: R (advanced), Matlab (advanced), Python, including libraries for geospatial analysis (advanced), Google Earth Engine (basic), Bash/Shell (basic), Javascript (basic), ArcGIS / QGIS (basic)

ACADEMIC AND PROFESSIONAL PROFILES

ORCID: 0000-0003-1614-3885 github: https://github.com/peterberr

Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=PUMnjmMAAAAJ&hl=en

LinkedIn: https://de.linkedin.com/in/peter-berrill-b56b7250

Website: https://peterberr.github.io/

Further information including a details of publications, teaching experience and skills, research interests, academic service, and involvement in scientific conferences is provided in the following pages.

SCIENTIFIC PUBLICATIONS

- Summary (Google Scholar): h-index (12), total citations (636 on June 30 2023)
- Peer-reviewed publications in scientific journals, as first author:
- **Berrill, P.**, E.J.H Wilson, J.L. Reyna, A.D. Fontanini and E.G. Hertwich. 2022. Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States, 2020-2060. *Nature Climate Change* 12(8): 712-718
- **Berrill, P.** & Hertwich, E. 2021. Material flows and GHG emissions from housing stock evolution in US counties, 2020-2060. *Buildings & Cities* 2(1): 599-617
- **Berrill, P.**, Gillingham, K. T., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. Drivers of change in U.S. residential energy consumption and greenhouse gas emission, 1990-2015. *Environmental Research Letters* 16: 034045
- **Berrill, P.**, K.T. Gillingham and E.G. Hertwich. 2021. Influence of housing policy and housing typology on residential energy demand in the United States. *Environmental Science & Technology* 55(4): 2224-2233 http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.0c05696
- **Berrill, P.**, T.R. Miller, Y. Kondo, and E.G. Hertwich. 2020. Capital in the American carbon, energy, and material footprint. *Journal of Industrial Ecology* 24(3): 589–600.
- **Berrill, P.** and E.G. Hertwich. 2018. Ground truthing the environmental benefits of a polygeneration system: when to combine heat and power? *Energy & Buildings* 173: 221–238. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enbuild.2018.05.020.
- **Berrill, P.**, A. Arvesen, Y. Scholz, H.C. Gils, and E.G. Hertwich. 2016. Environmental impacts of high penetration renewable energy scenarios for Europe. *Environmental Research Letters* 10(12): 123002. https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/11/1/014012

Publications in preparation, as first author:

Berrill, P., A. Javaid, N. Milojevic-Dupont, F. Nachtigall, F. Wagner, and F. Creutzig. 2023. Urban form influences travel distances, car ownership, and mode choice: evidence from 19 European cities. *Under Review* https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-2924076/v1

Peer-reviewed publications in scientific journals, as co-author:

- Van Ewijk, S., Chaudhary, S., **Berrill, P**. 2023. Estimating passenger emissions from airfares supports equitable climate action. *Environmental Research Letters*
- Jiang, M., Suo, C., Wu, L., **Berrill, P**. 2022. Consumption structure optimization for reducing energy footprint. *Economic Systems Research*
- Wang, T., **Berrill, P.**, Zimmerman, J. B., Rao, N.D., Min, J., & Hertwich, E. G. 2022. Improved Copper Circularity as a Result of Increased Material Efficiency in the US Housing Stock. *Environmental Science and Technology*, 56(7), 4565-4577
- Pauliuk, S., Heeren, N., **Berrill, P.,** Fishman, T., Nistad, A., Tu, Q., Wolfram, P., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. Global scenarios of resource and emission savings from material efficiency in residential buildings and cars. *Nature Communications*, 12(1), 5097
- Fishman, T., Heeren, N., Pauliuk, S., **Berrill, P.**, Tu, Q., Wolfram, P., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. A comprehensive set of global scenarios of housing, mobility, and material efficiency for material cycles and energy systems modeling. *Journal of Industrial Ecology*, 25(2), 305–320

- Peter Berrill C.V. June 2023
- Wang, T., **Berrill, P.**, Zimmerman, J. B., & Hertwich, E. G. 2021. Copper Recycling Flow Model for the United States Economy: Impact of Scrap Quality on Potential Energy Benefit. *Environmental Science and Technology*, 55(8), 5485–5495
- Pauliuk, S., T. Fishman, N. Heeren, **P. Berrill**, Q. Tu, P. Wolfram, and E.G. Hertwich. 2020. Linking service provision to material cycles: A new framework for studying the resource efficiency–climate change (RECC) nexus. *Journal of Industrial Ecology*: 25(2), 260-273
- Miller, T.R., **P. Berrill**, P. Wolfram, R. Wang, Y. Kim, X. Zheng, and E.G. Hertwich. 2019. Method for endogenizing capital in the United States Environmentally-Extended Input-Output model. *Journal of Industrial Ecology* 23(6): 1410–1424.
- Wang, C., X. Zheng, W. Cai, X. Gao, and **P. Berrill**. 2017. Unexpected water impacts of energy-saving measures in the iron and steel sector: Tradeoffs or synergies? *Applied Energy*. 205: 1119-1127
- Reports, Book chapters, pre-prints, papers under review, and theses, as first and co-author:
- Cabeza et al (2022) Chapter 9 Buildings, in IPCC AR6 Climate Change 2022 Mitigation of Climate Change
- Hertwich, E., Lifset, R., Pauliuk, S., Heeren, N., Ali, S., Tu, Q., Ardente, F., **Berrill, P.**, Fishman, T., Kanaoka, K., Kulczycka, J., Makov, T., Masanet, E., & Wolfram, P. (2020). *Resource Efficiency and Climate Change:*Material Efficiency Strategies for a Low-Carbon Future.
- Chertow, M.R., K.S. Kanaoka, T.R. Miller, **P. Berrill**, P. Wolfram, N. Heeren, and T. Fishman. 2020. The Systems Science of Industrial Ecology: Tools and Strategies Toward Meeting the Sustainable Development Goals. In *Science, Technology, and Innovation for Sustainable Development Goals*, ed. by Adenle A. Ademola, Marian R. Chertow, Ellen H. M. Moors, and David J. Pannell. Oxford University Press.
- **Berrill, P.** 2021. A Comparison of Strategies for Mitigation of Lifecycle Greenhouse Gases from Residential Buildings in the United States (Doctoral Thesis) Yale University. Supervisor Edgar G. Hertwich
- **Berrill, P.** 2015. Life cycle assessment of power systems with large shares of variable renewable energy (Masters Thesis) University of Graz. Supervisors Edgar G. Hertwich, Anders Arvesen
- **Berrill, P.**, Moran, P. 2013 Environmental Life Cycle Assessment of a University Building in Ireland (Bachelors Thesis) National University of Ireland, Galway. Supervisor Jamie Goggins

TEACHING EXPERIENCE:

During my PhD, I served as a teaching fellow six times, for four different courses. Tasks associated with this position include design and grading of homework assignments, assisting professors with communications to students and input to course design, and offering feedback and advice to students on course projects.

Academic Teaching fellow posts:

Urban Economics for Sustainability (Seminar), with Prof. Felix Creutzig
Industrial Ecology, with Prof. Marian Chertow and Dr. Stijn van Ewijk

2019 Energy Systems Analysis, with Prof. Narasimha Rao

2019, 2017 Green Building: Issues and Perspectives, with Mr. Peter Yost

2018 Energy Systems Analysis, with Prof. Edgar Hertwich

2017 Carbon Footprints: Modelling and Analysis, with Prof. Edgar Hertwich

Non-Academic Teaching experience:

2023 Tutor with 'Prometeruse' project which connects scientists with secondary

school students who develop a mini-research into a question related to

climate change

2009-2016 Trumpet Tutor to individual beginner trumpet students

Teaching training and qualifications:

2020 'Planning a Seminar or Lecture for an English-Speaking

> Audience', training at TU Berlin. Aimed at inclusive teaching of students with various cultural backgrounds whose first language is

not necessarily English

2016 Teaching English as a Foreign Language certificate from i-to-i,

accredited by Open and Distance Learning Quality Council

Selected guest classroom lectures:

2020 & 2021 Guest lecture in Industrial Ecology: Impacts Embodied in Trade 2019 Guest lecture in Green Building: Issues and Perspectives course:

"Trends and drivers of US residential energy consumption, 1990-

2015"

2018 Guest lecture in Industrial Ecology: "Input-Output Life Cycle

Assessment"

2017 Guest lecture in Industrial Ecology: "Life Cycle Assessment -

Introduction"

ACADEMIC SERVICE AND OTHER CONTRIBUTIONS

I was honoured to serve a contributing author to the Buildings chapter of the most recent IPCC Assessment Report (Working Group 3). My main responsibilities for this chapter involved assessing historical and projected evolutions of embodied and energy-related emissions in the building sector using an index decomposition approach, and contributing to the chapter text, particularly for describing the decomposition analyses and summarising research on 'sufficiency' mitigation strategies in the building sector.

I am an active member of the International Society for Industrial Ecology since 2017, and this year (2023) I was elected as a board member for the Life Cycle Sustainability Assessment section of the society, and invited to serve on the scientific committee for the upcoming conference in Leiden in July 2023. I contributed with other society members to a white paper summarising insights from industrial ecology for the circular economy, which is due to be published in summer 2023. In 2019 I led an advisory group within the society where we discussed and made recommendations to the society board on reducing conference-related air travel. I have served as a reviewer for numerous field and generalist scientific journals, listed in my CV. I organised an online poster session for the online Industrial Ecology Day conference in 2021. While I was a doctoral student at Yale School of the Environment, I acted as a student representative on a faculty search panel for a new professor in Industrial Ecology and Sustainable Systems.

I have been active in in-person and online scientific conferences and meetings, and a selection of conference and seminar presentations are summarised below.

ORAL PRESENTATIONS AT SCIENTIFIC CONFERENCES

Invited Presentation

30/06/2020: "Estimation of demolition and new construction of housing in US counties until 2060 -

Implications for building material reuse potential" - The 15th International Conference on Waste Management and Technology Zero-waste City High Level Forum (Online)

Presentations

20/09/2022: "Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States" – International Society for

Industrial Ecology – Socioeconomic Metabolism Conference, Wien (Austria)

03/06/2022: "Building and Shelter" Session chair and introductory presentation – ECCC Symposium, Berlin

(Germany)

25/05/2022: "Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States" – International Energy

Workshop, Freiburg (Germany)

- Peter Berrill C.V. June 2023
- 03/06/2020: "Housing policy, housing typology, and residential energy in the United States" Actionable Science for Urban Sustainability (Online)
- 08/07/2019: "Dynamic stock, energy and lifecycle analysis of residential buildings in the US" 10th biennial International Conference on Industrial Ecology (ISIE 2019), Beijing (China)
- 11/04/2019: "Drivers of residential energy consumption in the US and options for GHG reductions" Yale FES Research Day, New Haven (USA)
- 20/04/2018: "Making less bad things happen when we build houses and make our homes feel warm" (Up-Goer-Five presentation) Yale FES Research Day, New Haven (USA)
- 28/06/2017: "Environmental performance of university campus buildings: An energy system evaluation" 9th biennial International Conference on Industrial Ecology (ISIE 2019), Chicago (USA)
- 28/09/2016: "Life Cycle Analysis of Electricity Systems: High Penetration Renewable Scenarios and the Roles of Energy Storage and Grid Transmission" American Center for Life Cycle Assessment, LCA XVI, Charlestown (USA)
- 03/06/2016: "Environmental impacts of high penetration renewable energy scenarios for Europe" International Energy Workshop, Cork (Ireland)

INVITED SEMINAR PRESENTATIONS

- 12/05/2022: "Decarbonization pathways for the residential sector in the United States" MCC (Germany)
- 01/11/2019: "Drivers of change in residential energy consumption in the US, 1990-2015,

 The roles of housing age cohorts, fuel switching, and household size" Yale University (USA)
- 08/06/2018: "Reducing carbon, energy, and material footprints from the residential sector in the united states: the importance of capital stocks and energy supply systems" Waseda University, Tokyo (Japan)
- 03/08/2017: "Accounting for consumption of capital in the US Input-Output tables: approaches and impacts" Waseda University, Tokyo (Japan)

POSTER PRESENTATIONS AT SCIENTIFIC CONFERENCES/SCIENCE OUTREACH EVENTS

- 10/09/2022: "Urban form's influence on GHG intensity of urban mobility in European cities" Berlin Klima Tag 2022 (Germany)
- 21/06/2021: "Pathways for sustainable material use and GHG emission reductions from housing stock evolution in US counties to 2060" Industrial Ecology Day 2021 (Online)
- 23/05/2018: "Reducing carbon, energy, and material footprints from the residential sector in the US: The importance of capital stocks and energy supply systems" Industrial Ecology Gordon Research Conference, Les Diablerets (Switzerland)
- 27/06/2017: "Environmental performance of university campus buildings: An energy system evaluation" 9th biennial International Conference on Industrial Ecology (ISIE 2019), Chicago (USA)